[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, so, so, like, just to ask about the question about sotāpanna, because people obviously want to practice and find a teacher with a right view, that's probably a criterion for practice, and how they can judge who to follow, who to listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to realize that you don't have the criteria for what right is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have a criteria for what teacher knows what they talk about and which one of them doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only criteria a person has is this is agreeable and this is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not necessarily always corresponding to this is right and this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes disagreeable things are right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes agreeable things are wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes agreeable things are right, depending on what you find agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you kind of... usually it's going to be this person is acting in a way that fits with my image of what I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you question your image.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what a sotāpanna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has... you're going to have some notion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some... some... some ājahn will be more inspiring to you than the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: There has to be a starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't want to stop there and now just blindly defend that ājahn and not listen to any other one.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is this more inspiring to me?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to start, as I always say, with something that is least likely to be wrong, which is the suttas themselves, but that doesn't mean they read plainly, clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody is basically responsible for their own interpretation of most of the suttas, because they've been, you know, it's been so long time ago and they're so general and so condensed in meaning that, yeah, same passage can mean one thing and completely opposite thing for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be honest with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means I don't have the right criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means I better be careful when I choose to follow agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I better be careful when I choose to dismiss the disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, having just suttas available, not a teacher, is still some hope for attaining the right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, but there is a... there is a big gap between the suttas and when people approach it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There usually, on practical level, there has to be something in between, at least to direct you towards the suttas, how to read them rightly and regard them rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's where we spoke in one of the previous talks, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even those who said, you know, they're practicing alone and just suttas, they also have nilavira as a starting point, like... Well, yeah, yeah, there has to be something.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if they don't find any...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see there, that's it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they don't find, they won't find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only time they realize they found it, is when they become āryas themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, they won't need it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't be sure, unless you're a sotāpanna, that you, your teacher is a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you're a sotāpanna, then you will know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you wouldn't have been a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not a question of finding the right teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, until they find the right teacher...
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll never find the right teacher if they're looking for the right teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to find the right view on account of the teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you know that you found the right teacher when you stop needing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what can a putujana teacher can do for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can inspire people in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's highly unlikely they would be inspiring someone in virtue without inspiring them in the further wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a patujan is honest, transparent, and says, I don't know where you're suffering, but the way I understood the suttas is that sense-restraint is really necessary, and really important, and even if you don't get anywhere, as the Buddha said, if you spend the rest of the days of your life in tears of pains of sense-restraint, it's still better, and you're heading for heavens and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is, once you get to the stage of being a teacher, you are now in contact with praise, honor, gains.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's going to corrupt you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're... unless you kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's no right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's no right view, that's going to corrupt you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, you already corrupted yourself even before that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were teaching freedom from suffering while knowing you don't know the freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even before praise and blame, you were already corrupted.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean, like I said that in previous talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you kind of inadvertently... Oh, I found this helpful, but you're presenting it as dhamma, but you don't know whether that's dhamma or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a very unwholesome thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't accidentally be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot accidentally stumble upon nibbāna and then become enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the corruption started by giving in to the, you know, established norms of whatever teacher today is, knowing or not knowing or ignoring the fact that you don't know the way of suffering yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a plainest contradiction in terms that it can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know the escape and here you are preaching the escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some teachers probably think they know the way of suffering there are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure some would kind of, yeah, think they know, but many times, many times, I heard, like, senior monks say, I'm not a sotāpanna, but then spend an hour giving you dhamma talk, telling you how to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just I'm not.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nobody.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's nothing to attain.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you practice, the less you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then go on and teach.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you declare or not, or whatever, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, well, I mean, it depends.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is your place to judge that for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not your place to judge that for everybody else in the world, but you had to judge for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you have to judge what you just judged for yourself and not take that for granted either.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then see why you judged it in a certain manner and not in the other one.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you will become transparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just thinking there's so few places in the world where one can ordain and practice, and so many choices, and then...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, you go to any monastery where you can get training vinaya, and then you have to just be quite independent in some way, but there's also can have a disadvantage of too independence, you become arrogant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, monastery doesn't make you practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-monastery doesn't make you non-practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You yourself do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're looking for a place so you can practice, means you're looking for practice at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, well, that's why we said that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to recognize it... you're fully responsible for practicing or non-practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're not in the monastery, you're fully responsible for restraint or non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not mean, because I'm not in the monastery, I don't need to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or because, if I get into monastery, I will automatically be restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you start thinking like that, then you really... certainly, in the beginning, won't matter as much where you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a sense of, like, I really need this environment, and there is no practice without it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will only matter in that indirect sense whereby, are you constantly bombarded with things you have to say no to, and restrain, and endure, or are you not?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can actually reach, find certain, quite a lot of circum... like, like, uh... ways of living, even without being in the monastery, they would be quite secluded and non-distracting, and not really, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can even see the practice lack of people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they change the place, the practice is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even worse, they leave the monastery, still as a monk, and they disrobe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even the rules have not been kept internally, it was all done by the circumstances and just following what others do and say.
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment you step out of that bubble, you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no other criteria, reference point, making independence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Surrender to the form, as I was told once.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surrender to the form.
[SPEAKER_00]: The, you know, the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The kind of structures of the monastery surrender to all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good advice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't take responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let the monastery be your... yeah, your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is not quite what the Buddha meant when he said, be an island for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That even critical monks wanting seclusion, they just should surrender to pujas and gathering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: People have their reasons.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because once you find that right place, the right place of practice,
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, it's... it reveals how ridiculous or how unnecessarily external circumstances are...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean the genuine right place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, when you find the real right place of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely, absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Internal place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in short, it's talking about the real home.
[SPEAKER_00]: The real home.
[SPEAKER_00]: The real home, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you were saying before.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: What's important, what's wholesome and unwholesome, has nothing to do with the things out there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the things that it had something to do with, are the things you abandon by keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it's on to you to develop the principle within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, literally, like, again, just think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your place, if your practice depends on a place,
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have a say over places?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have a say over duration?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have a say over the environment not changing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you do, will you have that say forever?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, sooner or later, that has to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, then, your practice will have to go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always say, like, no, imagine, like, today, you'll end up in a hospital.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the end of the day, you have to be hospitalized for something.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would your mind... would your mind remain equanimous, indifferent, in the same sense it is on top of a mountain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it should be, if you've been practicing rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bombarded by elements, enduring the words and company and discomfort, it still should not make any difference, because that's not where the difference is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if the thought of it already freaks you out, means, well, there you go, loads of work for you to do, and that's exactly what needs to be dealt with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what I mean, like, even when people go in the forest in seclusion, they do it out of that projected external reason, which is just because it pleases them, makes things easier at the time, so you don't have to deal with anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look, look, all the suttas talk about seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, once you have the right view, sure, you'll know exactly where the place of that seclusion is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that, it's a relative thing, seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, some people can live on top of a mountain and still live in company.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people can live surrounded by people, but be completely secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the company, again, is internal basis for desire for distraction, or non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be very curious, not just... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Physically boarding yourself, you know, in a stone cell.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Padded stone cell.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where you won't be able to hear, see or... nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing of the external world.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can also say that that place of practice is incomparable to any other, to a physical place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because it's not a place, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a physical place.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it overrides all physical, beautiful places in the world that you could ever imagine, ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some, you know, secluded mountain stream, the deers... Well, there was the suttas as well, when the Buddha... What was that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, when the man saw the bed by the road, like a bed of leaves and twigs, he says, well, whoever slept here last night must have had a rough night.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, no, among those who sleep well, I'm the foremost who sleeps well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the man didn't understand and he says, imagine you're a king with like, I don't know, 15 wives that attend to your every need and
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the high luxurious bed and for everything you can possibly imagine in terms of the place, comfort, sense, desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, say, wouldn't on some occasion be, like that king, wouldn't his mind be gripped by something unpleasant on account of somebody said something or somebody didn't do something, so that fever, he could not sleep at night, no amount of wives could attend to him for the... he would be gripped by that ill will or lust or pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, yes, yes, that's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, but what about those who are incapable of experiencing that kind of internal pain, grief, fever,
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's actually the root of the disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not where you sleep, or how you sleep, or what elements you endure, or what elements you don't endure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, circumstances become irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: All become equal in places.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You went beyond them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, the whole... Was it Sābhāsa Sutta?
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole set of kilesas to be abandoned simply by enduring them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Heat, cold, words of others, discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you become strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, like when the... when a person's mind gets touched by the pleasant feeling, the body gets touched by the pleasant feeling, as in the possibility for pleasure arises, they cannot resist it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot help but crave towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they're touched by the unpleasant feeling, again, they could just bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always an option.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't help crave against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because they're touched in the first place, but because they can't help either crave for more or for less of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how deeply circumstances are irrelevant in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even your craving is not in circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that... the agreeable and disagreeable is not... it's... in the circumstance, it's not the route for lust and aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your own ignorance of agreeable and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that can only become apparent on the basis of sensory strength and the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one criteria that Kutujana can use for finding the right teacher or the teaching
[SPEAKER_01]: is... why do I want to practice dhamma in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Be very, very clear what you want, and then you will become clearer as to what you need.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know what you need, because you don't know what you really want.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think most of us start... people start practicing for the wrong reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we're just inspiring... Well, not being clear about your reasons is a wrong reason in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why do you want to practice dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, I'll seek for the teachings that talk about freedom from suffering, and not talk about some random anecdotal stories and something that will entertain me and help me fall asleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can question any further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I value freedom from suffering, while I'm not being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I were to think about it, how would that freedom from suffering be developed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Through suffering or through extreme pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is more likely?
[SPEAKER_01]: You already get the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that are valuable to... to be, you know, obtained in the world, do you have to work for them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you just get them through pure pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is more often?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is more common?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I should then seek for that with... for the teachings that tell me... talk about freedom from suffering and also make me feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can, even with an ignorant, putuginous mind, you can still develop kind of accurate criteria, if you're willing to accept the discomfort of it.